A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Office Files of William D. Carmichael FA711
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subjects, 1968-1989; 5; 4.65 Cubic Feet
  - Mid-decade Review, 1986-1987 (Box 25, Folder 245-247)
  - National Development Models, 1978-1979 (Box 25, Folder 248)
  - National Institute of Social Sciences, 1974-1977 (Box 25, Folder 249)
  - Overseas Compensation, 1968-1981 (Box 25, Folder 250, Box 26, Folder 251-253)
  - Overseas Compensation – tax aspects, 1977-1980 (Box 26, Folder 254-255)
  - Population Council, 1976-1979 (Box 27, Folder 256-258)
  - Program planning functions, 1985-1987 (Box 27, Folder 259)
  - Program Related Investments – Hicks, Dan, 1986-1987 (Box 27, Folder 260)
  - Program Review, 1985-1989 (Box 27, Folder 261-263, Box 28, Folder 264-267)
  - Program Support – proposed budget, 1988-1989 (Box 28, Folder 268, Box 29, Folder 269)
  - Public Management in Developing Countries, 1972-1974 (Box 29, Folder 270-272)
  - Research Competition in International Security and Arms Control, 1979-1981 (Box 29, Folder 273)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Staff in India, 1988 (Box 29, Folder 274)
  - Rural Poverty and Resources Program Staff Meeting in Cairo, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 275)
  - Snow, Phillip, 1983 (Box 29, Folder 276)
  - Staff luncheons, 1976-1981 (Box 30, Folder 277)
  - Sutton, Francis X., 1981-1986 (Box 30, Folder 278)
  - Women's Program, 1977-1985 (Box 30, Folder 279-283, Box 31, Folder 284-285)
- Board of Trustees, 1978-1989; 6; 2.85 Cubic Feet
  Correspondence, memoranda, agendas, reports, briefing books and travel information, relating primarily to overseas meetings coordinated by William Carmichael and his staff. Included in some files are Carmichael's handwritten notes on meeting proceedings, and outlines for several of his presentations to the Board. Also a few files of correspondence with, and travel reports by, individual board members. Meeting minutes, dockets, reports and committee files previously and separately collected by the Archives are not included here. Access restricted.
  - Dahrendorf, Ralf, 1981-1983 (Box 31, Folder 286)
  - Ellis, James, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 287)
  - McNamara, Robert S., 1983 (Box 31, Folder 288)
  - Marshall, Dorothy, 1981-1983 (Box 31, Folder 289)
  - Meetings, 1981-1988 (Box 31, Folder 290-298, Box 32, Folder 299-309, Box 33, Folder 310-313)
  - Meetings in Africa - Briefing materials, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 314-315)
  - Meetings in Africa - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 316, Box 34, Folder 317)
  - Meetings in Africa - Nairobi program, 1982 (Box 34, Folder 318)
  - Meetings in Africa - Schedules, 1982 (Box 34, Folder 319-320)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Briefing book, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 321)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 34, Folder 322)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Country briefings, 1986 (Box 35, Folder 323-327, Box 36, Folder 328)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Security, 1985-1986 (Box 36, Folder 329)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Travel briefings, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 330)
  - Meetings in Latin America - Travel schedules, 1986 (Box 36, Folder 331)
  - Meetings in New Delhi – itinerary, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 332)
  - Meetings in Southeast Asia - Background readings, 1989 (Box 36, Folder 333-334, Box 37, Folder 335-336)
  - Meetings in Southeast Asia - Itineraries, 1989 (Box 37, Folder 337-338)
  - Meetings in Southeast Asia - Planning, 1988-1989 (Box 37, Folder 339)
  - Meetings in Southeast Asia - Schedules, travel and accommodations, 1989 (Box 37, Folder 340-341, Box 38, Folder 342)
  - Milliken, William, 1983 (Box 38, Folder 343)
  - Preiskel, Robert, 1983 (Box 38, Folder 344)
  - Rabb, Harriet S., 1981-1983 (Box 38, Folder 345)
  - Spencer, Edson W., 1981 (Box 38, Folder 346)
- Chronological Correspondence Files, 1971-1989; 7; 2.66 Cubic Feet
  This series contains Dr. Carmichael's chronological correspondence files dating from 1971 to 1989. The files from October 1981 to 1989 are arranged in yearly increments and then alphabetically by recipient's last name.
  The files begin with Dr. Carmichael's appointment as head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean (OLAC) and continue through to his retirement in 1989. During this time, he also directed the Middle East and Africa (MEA) office and served as Vice President of the Developing Countries Program (DCP). The files include correspondence with and memoranda about grantees, including approvals for grant extensions and modifications. Memoranda in the files also discuss issues regarding Foundation policy such as budget review questions and internal affirmative action policy.
  Related Materials
  Other information about the Africa and Middle East (AME) Programs can be found in Program Staff Files, 1965-1976, 1987-1994 (FA503). Additional information about the Developing Countries Program can be found in the Program Staff Files, 1960-1983. The files were maintained by Elisa Scatena and Richard W. Dye, both of whom reported to Dr. Carmichael as head of DCP. A portion of these files have been transferred to Rockefeller Archive Center as FA528 Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Program Staff Files, 1973-1978. Ford Foundation records, Developing Countries Program, Vice President, Office files of William D. Carmichael, 1968-1989, document his oversight of the administration and program activities of Foundation field offices around the world, and of New York-based program staff responsible for grants in developing countries.
  - Chron File, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 347-349)
  - Chron File, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 350-353)
  - Chron File, 1973 (Box 39, Folder 354, Box 40, Folder 355-357)
  - Chron File, 1974 (Box 40, Folder 358-361)
  - Chron File, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 362-363)
  - Chron File, 1976 (Box 41, Folder 364)
  - Chron File, 1977 (Box 41, Folder 365)
  - Chron File, 1978 (Box 41, Folder 366)
  - Chron File, 1979 (Box 41, Folder 367, Box 42, Folder 368)
  - Chron File, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 369-370)
  - Chron File, 1981 January-September (Box 42, Folder 371)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1981 October-1982 March (Box 42, Folder 372)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1982 April-December (Box 42, Folder 373, Box 43, Folder 374-375)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1983 (Box 43, Folder 376-379)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1984 (Box 43, Folder 380-381, Box 44, Folder 382-383)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1985 (Box 44, Folder 384-386)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1986 (Box 44, Folder 387-388, Box 45, Folder 389)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1987 (Box 45, Folder 390-392)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1988 (Box 45, Folder 393-394)
  - Chron File (alphabetical), 1989 January-September (Box 45, Folder 395)
- Reports and Program Files, 1964-1990; 8; 1.14 Cubic Feet
  The reports in this series were originally separated by the Ford Foundation from the rest of Carmichael's collection for further cataloging. The reports were added back after documentation indicated the material belonged with Carmichael's paper. Many of the reports in this series are from the Urban Mathematics Collaborative Project funded by the Ford Foundation.
  - Conference on Community Development, San Juan, Puerto Rico - Part 1, 1964 December 14; ¼ inch audio cassettes (Box 1, Reel AV 15740)
    Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Conference on Community Development, San Juan, Puerto Rico - Part 2, 1964 December 14; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Reel AV 15741)
  - Developing Countries Program - Program Reviews, 1979-1986 (Box 45, Folder 396)
  - Conference on International and Regional Institutions, 1984 November 7-8 (Box 46, Folder 397)
  - Program Report 90-1, The Urban Mathematics Collaborative Project: Report to the Ford Foundation on the 1988-89 School Year, Wisconsin Center for Education Research, 1990 March (Box 46, Folder 398)
    Authors: Norman L. Webb, Susan D. Pittelman, Thomas A. Romberg, Allan J. Pitman, James A. Middleton, Elizabeth M. Fadell, and Marilyn Sapienza
  - Program Report 87-4, 1986 Annual Report to the Ford Foundation: The Urban Mathematics Collaborative Project, Wisconsin Center for Education Research, 1987 March (Box 46, Folder 399)
    Authors: Thomas A. Romberg, Norman L. Webb, Allan J. Pitman, and Susan D. Pittelman
  - Program Report 88-1, The Urban Mathematics Collaborative Project: Report to the Ford Foundation on the 1986-87 School Year, Wisconsin Center for Education Research, 1988 January (Box 46, Folder 400)
    Authors: Norman L. Webb, Susan D. Pittelman, Thomas A. Romberg, Allan J. Pitman, and Steven R. Williams,
  - The Urban Mathematics Collaborative Project: Report to the Ford Foundation on 1987-88 School Year, Wisconsin Center for Education Research, 1989 March (Box 46, Folder 401)
    Authors: Norman L. Webb, Susan D. Pittelman, Thomas A. Romberg, Allan J. Pitman, Elizabeth M. Fadell, and James A. Middleton
  - Whitney Young Memorial Lecture Field Responses to Franklin Thomas, 1986 (Box 47, Folder 402)
  - West Africa Human Rights Program Report, Tony Hodges, 1989 September (Box 47, Folder 403)
  - Trip Notes from Various Authors (From Files of Alice Brown), 1987-1989 (Box 47, Folder 404)
  - Archival Cataloging Documents, 1990 (Box 47, Folder 405)